<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Life on Mohit&#39;s Page</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/life/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Life on Mohit&#39;s Page</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Mohit Kumar</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What Should I Do With My Life?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/raw/what_should_i_do/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/raw/what_should_i_do/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is not meant to be a guide or a solution, It&amp;rsquo;s a personal reflection on life and finding meaning.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The biggest question we all ask ourselves is simple but hard: &amp;ldquo;What should I do with my life?&amp;rdquo; Can we get it right, or are we all just stuck?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We live in a world that loves doom and gloom. Movies, books, news, social media—everything focuses on bad endings and dark futures. We eat this stuff up, and it makes us feel like nothing matters. Look around and you&amp;rsquo;ll see it everywhere: people are lonelier, they move less, they don&amp;rsquo;t connect with others or even themselves. The old ways of finding meaning seem broken.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>This is not meant to be a guide or a solution, It&rsquo;s a personal reflection on life and finding meaning.</p></blockquote>
<p>The biggest question we all ask ourselves is simple but hard: &ldquo;What should I do with my life?&rdquo; Can we get it right, or are we all just stuck?</p>
<p>We live in a world that loves doom and gloom. Movies, books, news, social media—everything focuses on bad endings and dark futures. We eat this stuff up, and it makes us feel like nothing matters. Look around and you&rsquo;ll see it everywhere: people are lonelier, they move less, they don&rsquo;t connect with others or even themselves. The old ways of finding meaning seem broken.</p>
<p>I know this feeling well. I used to be active and involved in life. But after losing someone in my family, everything felt pointless. Why not just stay in my room, watch movies, play games, and do nothing? The world didn&rsquo;t give me any good reason to try. I got sucked in the dark hole of nihilism. It was such a dark place that I just couldn&rsquo;t get out of it anymore. I was so lost in my thoughts that I forgot to live.</p>
<p>When everyone is just so happy and content, things start to feel empty when you go through such stuff. In India the mourning of a loved one is so sad, it&rsquo;s like the world has come to a halt. Even after 2 years, I can&rsquo;t shake the feeling of loss.</p>
<p>Then what is the point of living? When you will just die one day ? A gripping question everyone is immediatly faced with in that situation. If death is the end, then why should I live ?</p>
<p>Things were gloomy for months , I didn&rsquo;t want to work but I had to. I was just so lost in my thoughts that I forgot about small things, suddenly i started forgetting things that i just did. It was so sad.</p>
<p>I started watching tv shows and anime to distract myself, I thought that if i just always be engaged in something i would eventually forget about it. But it didn&rsquo;t work.</p>
<p>I binge watched entire runs of shows that i would never watch, i binge watched entire runs of anime that i would never watch, i binge watched entire runs of movies that i would never watch. I wanted it to work, I tried more and more but it didn&rsquo;t work.</p>
<p>Around same time I watched a video on Wojak, he&rsquo;s an online character who goes through stuff and most of the times he&rsquo;s in weird situations. In one of the videos , wojak just went outside for a night walk. With no one in street , he just started walking and walking and walking.</p>
<p>Then he just sits on a park bench and just stares at the sky. Just kept staring at it for a while. Then he just started walking again.</p>
<p>Wojak is sad, depressed all the time but still he just lives by. Why ?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
